Guide to the KUED-TV productions audio-visual collection 1966-2010
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
KUED-TV productions audio-visual collection
1966-2010
University of Utah Libraries, Special Collections Audio Visual Archives Special Collections 295 South 1500 East Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860 (801) 581-8864
A0431
KUED-TV (Television station: Salt Lake City, Utah)
64 VHS videocassettes, 11 DVDs, 83 compact discs, 1 U-matic videocassette, 1 Betacam videoassette, 1 Mini-DV videocassette, 1 Fuji D3001 videocassette and 1 16mm film
The KUED-TV productions audio-visual collection (1966-2010) consists of recordings of local and regional television programs produced by or for KUED-TV. Most of the programs focus on topics related to Utah or the American West. KUED-TV is a Public Broadcasting Service (PBS) affiliated television station brodcasting from the University of Utah.
Organizational History
KUED is a Public Broadcasting Service (PBS) affiliated television station that has operated in conjunction with the University of Utah since 1958. In addition to airing nationally syndicated PBS programs KUED produces and airs television programs and documentaries made by local and regional filmmakers and about local and regional issues. KUED was the recipient of the first Rocky Mountain Emmy Award of Excellence for the Best Overall TV Station, which recognizes the station's commitment to serving the community through its productions and outreach programs. The Rocky Mountain Emmy Awards represent a division of the National Academy of Television Arts and Sciences that honors productions from Arizona, New Mexico, Utah, Wyoming and El Centro, California. Based in Salt Lake City, Utah, KUED now broadcasts on digital channels 7.1 (KUED), 7.2 (KUED World) and 7.3 (KUED V-me, a Spanish language station).
The KUED-TV productions audio-visual collection (1966-2010) consists of recordings of local and regional television programs produced by or for KUED-TV. Most of the programs focus on topics related to Utah or the American West.
The materials are arranged in loose chronological order.
Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.
See also the KUED-TV promotional materials (Acc 409) and records Acc 176, Acc 355, and Acc 374 in the University Archives Records Management Division of Special Collections.
Public television--Utah--History--Sources; Educational television stations--Utah--History--Sources; Arts, Humanities, and Social Sciences; Journalism; Material Types; Moving Images; Moving images
- Press and Politics I (101), undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 1)
  53:19 minutes
- Press and Politics II (102), undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 2)
  58:00 minutes
- On the Medical Edge: Genetics Brain (101), undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 3)
  25:51 minutes
- On the Medical Edge: Cancer (102), undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 4)
  24:21 minutes
- On the Medical Edge: The Heart (103), undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 5)
- Wilderness: Utah's Great Debate, undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 6)
  58:08 minutes
- Insight: Norm Bangerter, undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 7)
  56:46 minutes
- Insight: Senator Jake Garn, undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 8)
  Producer/Director: Ken Verdoia
  From the fall of communism to his highly publicized flight as a space shuttle astronaut, Senator Garn offers unprecedented insight to his political career in this interview. He also speaks movingly about the personal tragedies and triumphs that marked his eighteen years in Washington. 56:46 minutes.
- Insight: Tom Korologas, undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 9)
  56:20 minutes
- Insight: J. Bracken Lee, circa 1986; VHS videocassette (Cassette 10)
  Producer/Director/Interviewer: Ken Verdoia
  An interview with J. Bracken Lee, Governor of Utah (1949-1957) and Mayor of Salt Lake City (1960-1972). Lee speaks out on his colorful political career including: his controversial years as Mayor of Price, Utah; political campaigns reaching from the Depression through the Vietnam era; his eight years as Governor; battles with the Internal Revenue Service; his management of the relationship between government and the LDS Church; numerous political comebacks, including his three terms as Mayor of Salt Lake City; the changing face of American politics. 58:00 minutes.
- Insight: Calvin Rampton, circa 1994; VHS videocassette (Cassette 11)
  Host/Producer: Ken Verdoia
  The triumphs, memories and struggles of a storied political career are at the heart of this program. Over twelve years as Governor, Calvin Rampton carved out a unique and popular niche in Utah, running against a current of fleeting political fortunes and partisan intrigue. 58:00 minutes.
- Insight: Mark Strand, undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 12)
  In an unprecedented interview with KUED Senior Producer Ken Verdoia, former national Poet Laureate Mark Strand speaks of his pending departure from the University of Utah, the influence of the West on his poetry, and the future of the humanities in a society. 28:00 minutes.
- Tribute: Maurice Abravanel, circa 1986; VHS videocassette (Cassette 13)
  Interviewer: Ricklen Nobis
  For forty years Maurice Abravanel served as a passionate force in Utah's fine arts community. In a thoughtful, candid interview, Abravanel reflects on his storied career as conductor and musical director of the Utah Symphony. Sometimes humorous...sometimes caustic...but always heartfelt, The Maestro offers penetrating insight into life and the arts in his adopted home site. Re-issued in 1993 at the time of Abravanel's death at age 90
- Bruce Babbitt: Challenge, Change and the American West, circa 1994; VHS videocassette (Cassette 14)
  In his most comprehensive broadcast interview to date, Secretary Babbitt discusses his views on preservation, development and the emergence of a Anew land ethic@ for hundreds of millions of acres of publicly owned land...land that dominates the future of the American West. 57:00 minutes.
- Scott Matheson: Reflections, circa 1985; VHS videocassette (Cassette 15)
  Recollections of Utah Governor Scott M. Matheson on his eight years of service (1977-1985). This program was originally broadcast in 1985 as Matheson prepared to leave office, and was re-edited for broadcast in 1990 as a memorial program after his death. During the program, Matheson discusses his part in redefining the role of Governor, changes in the federal/state relationship, the execution of Gary Gilmore, nuclear weapons testing and its health implications, political campaigns and his relationship with Republican legislative majorities, and the John Singer case. Joined by his wife Norma Matheson, for the second half of the interview, Matheson discusses the private aspects of public service, the significance of a heart attack suffered during his second term, and his philosophical approach to public service. Re-edited for broadcast in 1990. 60:00 minutes.
- J. D. Williams: A University Portrait, undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 16)
  In this University Portrait, Williams reflects on his Aforty year love affair@ with the University of Utah, his involvement in national and local political issues, and his deep personal commitment to the 20,000 students who studied under his guidance. A fierce defender of political liberalism and involvement, AJ.D.@ is also one of Utah=s most recognized authorities on the Constitution of the Unites States of America.
- A Matter of Principle: Polygamy in the Mountain West, undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 17)
  A Matter of Principle provides an unprecedented look at the history, controversy, and contemporary practice of polygamy in the American West.
- River of Stone: The Powell Expedition, undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 18)
  KUED retraces Major Powell's historic expedition and charts the changes that occurred with the subsequent use and abuse of the river system he charted. Dramatic footage of the region is alternated with some of the first photographs ever taken of the territories Powell explored. Interviews with experts are combined with Powell's writings to bring the history and controversies surrounding the river into focus.
- 30 Years to Justice, circa 1985; VHS videocassette (Cassette 19)
  An examination of the case of Bulloch V. United States. A group of sheepherders from southern Utah and their flocks are exposed to massive amounts of radioactive fallout during nuclear weapons testing at the Nevada Test Site in the early 1950s. Claiming to have suffered devastating losses, they undertake a thirty-year campaign seeking justice from the federal government. The case offers unique insight into operations of the Atomic Energy Commission among people downwind from the Nevada Test Site during the open-air weapons testing period. Featuring archival film and still photos from the era and nuclear weapons testing. 28:00 minutes.
- Frontier Code Blue, undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 20)
  Frontier Code Blue examines a quiet crisis in health care in the nation's most isolated areas. In hundreds of rural towns in the Mountain West, health care systems are in danger of collapse. Critical shortages of trained medical personnel leave many communities without any form of emergency care. Rural hospitals are closing at the rate of one per month under the strain of expensive technology and the inability to recruit physicians. Whether they could afford the care or not, nearly one million residents of the rural Mountain West have no access to medical care...simply because it does not exist. 58:00 minutes.
- Shades of Gray, undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 21)
  Through intimate portraits of families facing the challenges of caring for an aging population, Shades of Gray documents the explosive growth of the nation's elderly. The program also examines the potential impacts of the aging of America's Baby Boom generation. 58:00 minutes.
- Topaz, undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 22)
  Fifty years ago Japanese-American children pledged allegiance to the flag of America while caged behind the barbed wire at the desert encampment of Central Utah, known as Topaz. During WWII thousands of ethnic Japanese living in the U.S.--men, women, and children--were stripped of their constitutional rights, forced from their homes, and shipped to Topaz, a War Relocation camp near Delta, Utah. For over three years, this barren desert camp was their
- A Rising Voice: Hispanic Utah, undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 23)
  Producer/Director: Colleen Casto
  This program examines the history of Hispanic immigration, the rich diversity of culture and its contributions, as well as the challenges facing Hispanic Utahns today. Most Utahns are not even sure what the term AHispanic@ means yet it is projected that Hispanics, as the largest growing minority population in the nation, will play a major role in the future.
- Utah's Black Legacy, undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 24)
  Co-producer/Director: Jerry Carter
  Co-producer/Writer: Jane Maddock
  Blacks were in Utah long before the mass immigration of the white settlers. You=ll learn about these trappers, scouts and adventurers. The people tell about growing up in Utah, in the early years as well as today. Segregation, subtle discrimination, hatred, educational and religious closed-mindedness, and yes, great hope, characterize being back in Utah. This documentary provides insight into the black culture of Utah, its history, its contributions to Utah's communities and its challenges and aspirations for the future.
- Remembering David, undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 25)
  This documentary provides an intimate profile of a man who dared to make a difference in society's response to an often misunderstood epidemic. The program chronicles the final forty-two months in the life of David Sharpton, a man fighting a difficult battle in an unlikely location against tremendous odds. Starting in 1988, Sharpton embarked on an exhaustive crusade to educate the public on the challenges of living with AIDS. This program deals with sensitive issues related to death and dying and may not be suitable for children.
- Arctic Wars, undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 26)
  Producer/Director: John Howe
  Narrated by actor E.G. Marshall, Arctic Wars examines the fight for the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge. The oil industry speculates it holds vast deposits of oil. The controversy of whether to develop will be the environmental debate of the 1990s and will shape the future.
- Grizzly: The Shining Mountains, undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 27)
  29:20 minutes
- The Great West Collection: The Last Cowboys, circa 1991; VHS videocassette (Cassette 28)
  Narrated by Joseph Campanella, The Last Cowboys provides a loving look at a truly American tradition. The trail winds through the world of today's cowboys as they live and work in the shadow of the Old West. 60:00 minutes.
- A Desert Sea, circa 1993; VHS videocassette (Cassette 29)
  Producer: John Howe
  Hosted by author Terry Tempest Williams, A Desert Sea reveals the mysteries of Utah's Great Salt Lake. From prehistoric Lake Bonneville to one of America's last shorebird sanctuaries, the program contrasts stark desert landscapes with a wealth of teeming wildlife and natural resources. 58:00 minutes.
- Return of the Wolves, circa 1989; VHS videocassette (Cassette 30)
  It's been 60 years since the mournful howl of the wolf was heard in Yellowstone. KUED chronicles the controversial attempts to reintroduce the wolf into Yellowstone. Containing rare footage, this program sheds new light on this feared and often misunderstood animal. 58:00 minutes.
- The Environment and You, undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 31)
  The Environment and You explores the critical issues of air quality and recycling. In two segments (A Darkening Sky, 23 minutes; Our Fragile Earth, 16 minutes), the video presents the dilemma and considers the solutions. 39:00 minutes.
- Atomic Stampede, circa 1994; VHS videocassette (Cassette 32)
  Producer: Ken Verdoia
  It was a time of opportunity and failure, virtue and deceit, and staggering human costs. Fortunes were made and lost in the blink of an eye during America's Cold War uranium boom. In this powerful documentary, KUED sheds new light on this forgotten chapter of our nation's history. 58:00 minutes.
- The Man and the Mountains: Paul Petzoldt, circa 1994; VHS videocassette (Cassette 33)
  He was a ground breaking mountaineer, an innovator in climbing, safety and survival. He developed a cutting edge approach while educating three generations of Americans on wilderness leadership and self-discovery. In a rare and candid interview, he talks of his life at the top of the world. With the Majestic Teton range of western Wyoming as his backdrop, he recounts dangerous early climbing experiences, his breathtaking expeditions to the world's most challenging summits, and the evolution of a new ethical standard for enjoying outdoor recreation without destroying the wild landscape. 57:00 minutes.
- The Faces of Utah, undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 34)
  A video presentation on the ethnic cultures of Utah. Hispanics, Blacks, Jews, Navajos and Southeast Asians are featured in this 5-segment program.
- Separate Journeys, circa 1993; VHS videocassette (Cassette 35)
  Members of the Native American (Ute), Mexican/Hispanic, Jewish, Japanese, and Greek communities share personal experiences regarding their immigration to (or relocation in) Utah, and the consequent struggle to maintain their respective cultural identities. Performed by Repertory Dance Theatre, this 5-part video combines personal histories, dance, music, and photography to celebrate the rich ethnic and cultural heritage of Utah. 56:00 minutes.
- Utah Women Considered, circa 1995; VHS videocassette (Cassette 36)
  Producers: Louise Degn, Colleen Casto, Marie Cornwall
  Like a tapestry handed down from one generation to the next, Utah Women Considered weaves together the common threads among four generations of Utah women in three families-one Ute, one Hispanic, and one Anglo-Mormon. Through their personal stories, the documentary tells the larger story of the past century of Utah women. While chronicling the changing lives and times of Utah women, the program explores universal issues ranging from education and aging to family and professional life. 57:00 minutes.
- Hans Petersen's Tom Paine, circa 1994; VHS videocassette (Cassette 37)
  Produced by Elizabeth Searles; Directed by Ann Gallenson
  In an intimate dramatic performance, Salt Lake City radio personality Hans Petersen brings to life this celebrated figure from America's past. Petersen's one-man show traces Paine's life from his childhood in England to his revolutionary years in America to his near-execution in France to his lonely final days in New York. 55:00 minutes.
- Desert Dreams, circa 1989; VHS videocassette (Cassette 38)
  28:00 minutes
- Utah: A Portrait, circa 1995; VHS videocassette (Cassette 39)
  Produced by John Howe and written by William B. Smart
  From the sapphire waters of Bear Lake to the sunbaked Salt Flats, Utah is a place justly celebrated for its geographic splendor and diversity. Soar above Delicate Arch, the Great Salt Lake, the rugged peaks of the Uintas, and more in this stunning aerial portrait evoking the breadth and majesty of Utah's landscape. Combines sweeping aerial photography with words and music to create a colorful collage of this unique land. 58:00 minutes.
- Salt Lake City: Once Upon a Time, circa 1995; VHS videocassette (Cassette 40)
  Produced by Elizabeth Searles, written by Elizabeth Searles and Hans Petersen
  Once upon a time, there were no malls in Salt Lake City. Parking was abundant, and anything past 2700 South was considered Aout in of daily life revolved around the war effort. Streetcars bustled people downtown to shop at large elegant department stores like Auerbach's. The city was brimming with dance halls and grand movie houses. Everyone took the train to Saltair and Lagoon. It was a time when men wore hats, cars had running boards, and everyone dressed up to go downtown. KUED takes you on a nostalgic journey to those days with this delightful video scrapbook featuring hundreds of photos, archival footage, and interviews with the people who fondly remember Salt Lake City "once upon a time." 80:00 minutes.
- UTAH: The Struggle for Statehood parts 1-2, circa 1995; VHS videocassette (Cassette 41)
  Written, Produced and Directed by Ken Verdoia
  Parts 1 and 2. This documentary takes an often surprising look at Utah's path to statehood, from determined pioneers seeking a haven to back room lobbying and deal-making in the halls of Congress. Three years in the making, the series was shot on location in four states and features more than 200 speaking roles in its powerful retelling of Utah's 50-year march to admission as the 45th state. The film combines archival photographs, original footage, and interviews with historians and writers, together with moving written records of early Utah settlers, both famous and obscure. 150 minutes.
- UTAH: The Struggle for Statehood parts 3-4, circa 1995; VHS videocassette (Cassette 42)
  135 minutes
- Probing the Genetic Universe, circa 1997; VHS videocassette (Cassette 43)
  Written, Produced and Directed by Kathleen Weiler
  The impact of human genetics upon life and medicine inside and outside the laboratory is revolutionary. What geneticists discover in the lab today will profoundly change our lives tomorrow--from decisions about what we eat, to the way we prevent, diagnose and treat human disease, to ultimately, how we frame our philosophical questions about birth and death. 56 minutes.
- Brigham Young, circa 1997; VHS videocassette (Cassette 44)
  Written, Produced, and Directed by Ken Versoia
  A comprehensive film biography of Brigham Young. 150 minutes.
- Let the Women Vote!, circa 1997; VHS videocassette (Cassette 45)
  Produced and Directed by Louise Degn
  Looks at the social and political contexts surrounding woman's suffrage. From the homesteading tradition, in which western women engaged in hard labor with men, to the drafting of new constitutions for Western territories, and the effect of the civil war, the program reveals the many changes in America which brought about the women's movement in the West. 56 minutes.
  46.
- Utah's African-American Voices, circa 1999; VHS videocassette (Cassette 46)
  This program captures the African-American experience in Utah through interviews with historians, educators, community leaders, and the personal stories of both long-time residents and those new to Utah. 56 minutes.
  47.
- Utah's Greek-Americans, circa 2000; VHS videocassette (Cassette 47)
  Linking immigrant ancestors to today's vibrant community, Utah's Greek-Americans celebrates a cultural group steeped in generations of hard work, religious devotion, and family life. Part of KUED's Many Faces, Many Voices diversity outreach project, this documentary highlights contemporary Hellenic traditions through interviews and visits to the annual Greek festivals in Salt Lake City and Price, Greek Orthodox ceremonies, and more. 57 minutes.
- Tell Me: Joe Tippets, 1966 February 21; 16mm film, U-matic videocassette, Mini-DV videocassette (Reel 48)
  Joe Tippets, Director of the Federal Aviation Agency's Western Region is interviewed by Neal Maxwell for the Tell Me program on KUED. 30 minutes.
- Fire in the Hole, circa 2000; VHS videocassette (Cassette 49)
  Fire in the Hole examines the mine labor wars that shaped the West during the early 1900s. The documentary views the conflict in its social and historical context. It was a time when industrialists surged forward to form an unchecked elite, and tens of thousands of new immigrants made their way West to work low-paying, often dangerous jobs. Shot on location in seven states, the two-hour documentary uses archival photographs, interviews with historians and the powerful voices of those who fought the battles to illuminate this lost and compelling chapter of history. 120 minutes.
  50.
- Glen Canyon: A Dam, Water and the West, circa 1999; VHS videocassette (Cassette 50)
  KUED produced documentary about the construction of the Glen Canyon Dam, which would create one of the world's largest man-made bodies of water in a desert, while at the same time drowning a thousand years of human history...and a million years of natural history. 57 minutes.
  51.
- Joe Hill, circa 1998; VHS videocassette (Cassette 51)
  In this powerful and unprecedented documentary, KUED presents the story of Joe Hill, a labor organizer executed by the state of Utah in 1915. It's a story of a nation struggling with issues of justice, opportunity and the American Dream. 87 minutes.
  52.
- Flagship in the Desert: 150 Years at the University of Utah, circa 2000; VHS videocassette (Cassette 52)
  The remarkable saga of the University of Utah's 150 year history and its improbable emergence from a two-room rented school house to its status today as one of the top research universities in the world...which now attracts and educates people from all fifty states and 111 foreign countries. The one-hour video scrapbook includes interviews with faculty, alumni, current and past presidents; rare historical photographs; as well as performances of the University of Utah A Cappella Choir; and a gospel arrangement of Utah Man performed by the New Pilgrim Baptist Church Choir. 60 minutes.
- Promontory, circa 2002; VHS videocassette (Cassette 53)